well you believe it by first recognizing
that it will take time
it will take time
for the pressure to subside
especially once you stop giving in to
the prior modes of relieving the pressure
prior modes of relieving the pressure
such as centrality distraction company
with the increase of pressure because
you're not giving in to the old habits
of relieving the pressure you will then
have to endure and
and recognize that it's going to take a
while until the mind comes down
but the most important thing is to not
uh give in to those old ways of of
relieving the pressure
so
although it can seem worse it needs to
be so before it can get better that's uh
that's kind of how these things work
so relieving the pressure household like
once you're not giving into the
distraction the pressure will will will
start to well the pressure can be
relieved by sustaining the virtues
behavior so
so
again initially when the pressure is all
doubled up so to speak
the um
it just might even seem counterintuitive
that sensory strain and virtue would would
sensory strain and virtue would would
relieve this pressure but actually
if you sustain it it will because you're
not fueling anymore those habits that
have been pressuring even before
you started practicing sense restraint
so that's the
importance there to recognize is that
the pressure that you start with
then the pressure that increases through
the sense restraint it's actually all
the pressure of centrality all the
pressure desires that you have been
giving into before carelessly
thus that pressure has accumulated so
you have become even more dependent on
scratching the edge on relieving that
pressure so once you start uh refraining
from that it's going to hurt more but
that pain is not due to your restraint
as i said many does before
that pain is actually due to the nature
of sexuality that's now hitting you
harder because obviously your habits
were the ones of avoiding that very
nature you did not want to deal with it before
you did not want to deal with it before
if you practice that patience
and purify the virtue even in the lace
setting you will you know you will get to
you will you know you will get to
experience that um
the dryness that we spoke about before
dryness from the um you know these
sticky pressuring habits
of desires from before and then and then
you kind of
have a have a confirmation that the
pressure is not lessening in itself
because the nature of centrality remains
the same what has changed is that uh
your mind now is not perturbed on
account of the pressure if the pressure
that's there it's not pressuring you
uh that means basically you know there's
no pressure there's no pressure for you
so
you could see that the the pressure now
is contained within the nature of
sensuality in the same sense for example
you would see the uh
well the similar for poisonous drink say
the simile of
of a beautiful beverage that it's
actually laced with poison
so you used to drink it you used to
enjoy it but now you you sort of uh you
learned that
there is poison in it so the pressure of
drinking that
tasty beverage the habit
is still there but the knowledge of the
poison uh just it prevents you from from
doing it
you you still know you still can
remember the taste of it
how inside and enticing it was but now
the the knowledge that uh it will bring
you harm is just so established that you
don't even consider it for a second
drinking it
so in other words although the the
beverage hasn't changed the uh the
pressure the uh the taste the in the induciveness
the uh the taste the in the induciveness
of lust
in it is still there
but you have absolutely no desire for it
because the knowledge of uh of the
imminent implicit
uh inseparable danger from it is
apparent so when that
uh when that kind of perception is
developed then the sense restraint
then the sense restraint
becomes the basis for pressurelessness
so
for the absence of that pressure you now
see directly depending
on your virtuous behavior that has been
developed beforehand that has been
cultivated unbroken and sustained and
now the mind does not move on account of
pressures that are
encountered in the world and that's kind
of the whole point
it's not to stop perceiving things in
the world they used to cause you
pressure it's not about not ex not
seeing not not experiencing
that pressure in the world it's about
not being moved by it
so so that's even where the practice of
samadhi comes it's not about
pleasant abiding of thoughtlessness or
something uh
it's it's it's really just comes down to
practicing immovability in regard to
things they want to move you lust
aversion desire for distraction and
desire for distraction and
and similar
so
with everything that's going on
like in a household setting in a lay
life you could still
you could still
live quite wholesomely quite skillfully
without needing to compromise the
precepts and recognize that that is the
basis for you correctly and wholesomely
relieving that uh
mind that has that that that's been
living under the pressure
and and that's also opportunity basically to
and that's also opportunity basically to
to then develop samadhi in the same
sense because uh now as thing come com things
because uh now as thing come com things
come your way one way or the other
there is no more uh impulsive giving in
overwhelming giving into the like um
to the pressure that's been overwhelming
the mind you see it come and you see it
go away on its own
and any desire to act has been lessened
and obviously the more you develop this
principle it could even be completely eradicated
it could even be completely eradicated
so
that's the true belief from the pressure
whereby there is no more desire to act
on account of it desire to get rid of it
desire to deal with it
because all of those desires were rooted
in you being moved by the pressure in
the first place so former habits of
relieving the pressure must be abandoned
and that the lifestyle must be protected
and sustained how it is
where the mind does not move amidst
things that used to move it
so when the pressure's still there with
things that would exert pressure still
there yet no pressure is felt so so
that's pretty much some that's the goal
to strive for not to never see or
perceive that which pressures you or
used to pressure you it's simply to not
be moved on account of it one way or the
other and that's pretty much step closer to
and that's pretty much step closer to
the
true freedom so